<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chandru Subramanian</title>
    <description>A few experiments, some notes, and miscellaneous writing.</description>
    <link></link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Make haste slowly</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Globally, by early 2025, 29% of all newly written software functions relied on AI assistance&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;“AI-assisted coding reaches mainstream adoption.” &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;, 2025, www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado5344.&lt;/span&gt; (up from 5% in 2022). The unspoken implication: fire those pesky programmers and replace them with an API call. AI acolytes believe that all software development, indeed all knowledge work, is about to become obsolete; skeptics are convinced that over a trillion dollars have been wasted and a dot-com style collapse is imminent. All roads, it seems, lead to mass unemployment and a takeover by skynet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never a confident bunch, senior engineers are worried about a rapid devaluation of skills that were acquired over a lifetime. Worryingly, enrollment in undergraduate and graduate courses has decreased. If one can “vibe-code” software, then it’s just a matter of wishing the AI genie to solve problems. Learning is a fool’s errand. So do we look forward to a future with greater unemployment, fewer apprentices to the art of software development, and rapid loss in institutional understanding of complex human spaces? All cheered on by ungodly sums of VC money! What is conspicuous by its absence is meaningful conversation about societal good!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The roughly dozen folks at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.answer.ai/posts/2023-12-12-launch.html&quot;&gt;Answer.AI&lt;/a&gt;, led by Jeremy Howard and Eric Ries, are making a contrarian bet: what is needed most in this moment is a return to curiosity; a return to craftsmanship. They believe that what AI affords is the ability to cut deeply through layers of complexity. There is an affordable opportunity for humans to comprehend machine-scale systems. Their answer: a generalized compute platform called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fast.ai/posts/2025-11-07-solveit-features.html&quot;&gt;SolveIt&lt;/a&gt; that integrates AI with literate programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roman coins minted in the time of Emperor Augustus bore the emblem of the dolphin and anchor, symbolizing “festina lente” — make haste slowly. You may know the modern adage: “slow is smooth and smooth is fast.” SolveIt is a platform that enables iteratively solving problems while pair programming with an LLM. One step at a time. Named after a problem-solving method from the mathematician George Pólya&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Pólya, George. &lt;i&gt;How to Solve It&lt;/i&gt;. Princeton University Press, 1945.&lt;/span&gt;, SolveIt feels like an evolution of Jupyter notebooks (which allow exploration by combining code, data, and notes into a living document). In a marked departure from the “vibe-coding” tools, SolveIt (by design) slows down thinking and encourages exploration as the software is built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By pure serendipity, the enrollment deadline for the second SolveIt cohort was about a week after I quit my job (my first break in about 25 years!). Having missed Jeremy Howard’s previous courses, signing up was a no-brainer. There is something immediately different about this course. A few hundred folks from various timezones are on. The sessions are unpolished; perhaps the lack of gloss is the point. But there’s shared curiosity, almost like we wait for the results of a chemistry experiment. There is attention to detail. And there is kindness. Howard and Johno Whitaker run through problems from Advent of Code. A longtime skeptic of LeetCode-style challenges, I had written these off. But suddenly the puzzles are fun. Taking a problem, breaking it down into the smallest elements, and building it back. I am more traveller, less a tourist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These sessions traverse large distances. In sessions lasting roughly an hour (sometimes too much fun to mind the clock) we deeply explore how agents like Claude work. Building them from scratch. We set up cheap infrastructure outside the popular hyperscalers. We dip into linear algebra. I was never good at this, but suddenly I’m building intuition about matrix math. Eric jumps on and talks about harsh realities of the business side that plague innovators. Skills I previously assumed were the domain of polymaths and giants feel accessible. It has been years since I had written code, but like most managers, I did not start my career because of a deep love of managing managers of software engineers. Yes, this is work, but it is fun to write code again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anthropic CEO Dario Amodei writes, “Humanity is about to be handed almost unimaginable power, and it is deeply unclear whether our social, political, and technological systems possess the maturity to wield it.”&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Amodei, Dario. “Machines of Loving Grace.” 2024, darioamodei.com/machines-of-loving-grace.&lt;/span&gt; Perhaps Amodei is right. A few minutes on LinkedIn will tell you that you are obsolete and your peers have already solved all meaningful problems. AI skeptics will call LLMs a farce. Regardless, neither side offers a path for the motivated and skilled (and likely terrified).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a profession, coders experience high levels of imposter syndrome. The antidote isn’t more AI - it’s more human agency. When engineers approach problems with genuine curiosity rather than a rush to ship, they build systems they actually understand. Craftsmanship means taking small, deliberate steps. It requires breaking every hard problem into pieces small enough to hold in your head. This produces maintainable code because you can’t maintain what you never understood. It rebuilds confidence because imposter syndrome thrives on mystery, and curiosity dissolves mystery. The engineer who asks “why does this work?” doesn’t need mystical incantations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reject the noise. There are real problems waiting in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//make-haste-slowly</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//make-haste-slowly</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How this blog was made</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Setting up a blog is not difficult and you should create one. This blog is created using jekyll and is hosted for free on GitHub pages. It uses Bradley Taunt’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bradleytaunt/ET-Jekyll&quot;&gt;ET-Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rachel Thomas has an extremely well-written post on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@racheltho/why-you-yes-you-should-blog-7d2544ac1045&quot;&gt;why you should blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-should-probably-not-self-host&quot;&gt;You should probably not self-host&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is fun to setup software and host your own blog. In 2024, setting up wordpress is a commoditized skill. Self-hosting work is a fun procrastination. It will not make your writing better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Motion makes you feel like you’re getting things done. But really, you’re just preparing to get something done. When preparation becomes a form of procrastination, you need to change something. You don’t want to merely be planning. You want to be practicing.&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Clear, James. &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamesclear.com/taking-action&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taking Action.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; jamesclear.com, 20 Jan. 2020.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should focus on publishing content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-should-probably-not-use-medium&quot;&gt;You should probably not use medium&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Medium is a paywalled online publishing platform for reading authored articles. It is a marketplace for authors to publish content and get paid for it. My goal is to publish content - I don’t want people to pay for information that I would gladly give them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this stage of my career, I find less need for public addulation. I also don’t want to build a large following that I can monetize. My preference is contempt-free, nuanced, and respectful conversation. Drop me a note at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:comments@chandru.blog&quot;&gt;comments@chandru.blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-should-host-on-github-pages&quot;&gt;You should host on github pages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Github is easy to setup, the limits are reasonable, and it is free. Paying companies depend on GitHub so it is well maintained and monitored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, GitHub pages is a specially named public git repository. Any markdown content in this repo will be rendered automatically by GitHub. Markdown takes away the temptation to tinker with typography and layout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-should-use-jekyll&quot;&gt;You should use jekyll&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jekyll is a static site generator. It takes markdown pages and renders them into static html. Once converted, these files can be hosted on any webserver (such as GitHub pages).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-shoud-do-the-jekyll-tutorial&quot;&gt;You shoud do the jekyll tutorial&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing tutorials feels tedious. But a few minutes spent on &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/step-by-step/01-setup/&quot;&gt;this tutorial&lt;/a&gt; will give you an understanding of the terrain; it will make your journey easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you aren’t familiar with the ruby ecosystem, I would suggest that you understand common commands for the ruby package manager, &lt;a href=&quot;https://bundler.io&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bundle&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-few-easy-steps&quot;&gt;A few easy steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I assume that you have a basic understanding of git and GitHub. The git cli is powerful but I tend to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://desktop.github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub Desktop&lt;/a&gt; for more complex operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;setup-github-pages&quot;&gt;Setup GitHub Pages&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Excellent step by step documentation is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.github.com/en/pages/getting-started-with-github-pages/creating-a-github-pages-site&quot;&gt;GitHub docs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;repos&quot;&gt;Repos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub has the ability to &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.github.com/en/pages/setting-up-a-github-pages-site-with-jekyll/about-github-pages-and-jekyll&quot;&gt;detect jekyll configs and render&lt;/a&gt; html for you. However, I prefer to locally render markdown into html and then push that out to GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I prefer to keep my working copy in a different repo than the GitHub pages. My workflow looks something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use the working repo for authoring and generating content. Use git branching, merging, PRs for managing versions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generate the static content locally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Merge into the GitHub pages repo and push content to publish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;optional-setup-a-custom-domain&quot;&gt;Optional: setup a custom domain&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is probably the most complex portion of all of the setup. But it is isn’t that difficult. The instructions on &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.github.com/en/pages/configuring-a-custom-domain-for-your-github-pages-site/managing-a-custom-domain-for-your-github-pages-site&quot;&gt;GitHub docs&lt;/a&gt; are excellent.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//how-this-blog-was-made</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//how-this-blog-was-made</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>I prefer paper, maybe you should too</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I spent a lot of my life trying to master spencerian cursive. I never got any good at it. 
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use block capitals and use short phrases (3-5 words). I use a cheap mechanical pencil and an excellent hi-polymer eraser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with all the electronic options, I keep returning to paper. Mostly because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paper is distraction free&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It forces prioritization (a sheet of paper has a finite size)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You see everything at-once. Edits are easy and quick. You can (and should) color outside the lines.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Writing by hand makes you smarter.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can fold it and put it in your wallet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no shortage of apps for phones and laptops that do magical organizational things. YMMV but they don’t work for me mostly for the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On my phone, I have a choice between working on my goals (hard) and browsing the internet (fun). I usually end up choosing instant gratification over valuable.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The keyboard takes up half the screen and at any point I am zoomed in too close to be able to see the full picture. Easy to lose track of what is important and go back to binging hackernews.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making edits is high-friction. Zoom in, scroll, click to edit, type&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They provide customizations and too many options. I get distracted easily and spend too much time thinking about serif vs non-serif fonts for optimal readability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2023 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//i-prefer-paper-maybe-you-should-too</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//i-prefer-paper-maybe-you-should-too</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
